- Now that we know how to
assign oxidation states
to Carbon let's look at some
organic redox reactions,
and remember these definition
from general chemistry.
Oxidation involves an increase
in the oxidation state
and reduction involves a decrease
or a reduction in the oxidation state.
You might also remember that
loss of electrons is oxidation
and gain of electrons is reduction.
So, LEO the lion goes GER as
a good way to remember that.
Let's look at this starting compound here
and this reaction, and let's figure out
whether the starting compound
has been oxidized, reduced, or neither.
If you look at these
three carbons on the left
and these three carbons on the right.
All right, there's no
change to those carbons
so there should be no change
in the oxidation states of those carbons
but when you look at
this carbon right here,
the one I just marked in yellow, right,
on the left it's bonded to,
let me go ahead and draw
that out, Is double bonded to an oxygen,
and on the right it's
bonded to a hydrogen,
and on the left it's bonded to a carbon.
But on the right here
that same carbon, right,
is now bonded to an oxygen on the right.
So, it still double bonded it to an oxygen
and has a, has a bond
to a carbon on the left,
but on the right now,
it has a bond to an OH.
So, that carbon has likely
changed its oxidation state
and we can go ahead and
find the oxidation state
using what we learned in the last video.
So, remember you need to put
in your bonding electrons.
So, let's put in our
bonding electrons here.
Each bond consists of two electrons.
All right, so we know that when
we're doing oxidation states
we need to think about
electronegativity differences
and carbon is more
electronegative than hydrogen.
So, we assign both of
those electrons to carbon.
Oxygen is more electronegative than carbon
so oxygen takes all
four of those electrons.
And when we get to carbon versus carbon
we can assume that those carbons have
the same electronegativies
and therefore for two electrons
we're gonna split those two electrons up.
We're gonna give one
electron to one carbon
and the other electron
to the other carbon.
So, this carbon is
surrounded by three electrons
and we know carbon should have,
we know carbon is supposed to have
a number of four valence
electrons around it.
So, carbon's supposed to have four.
In our dot structure here
Carbon only has three.
Let me highlight them.
One, two, and three.
So, four minus three gives us plus one
which is the oxidation
state for this carbon.
So, this carbon right here
has an oxidation state
of plus one on the left.
What about on the right?
Let's go ahead and put in
our bonding electrons, right.
So, we know that each bond
consists of two electrons.
Let me put those in here.
And again, we think
about electronegativity.
This time on the right, this carbon
is bonded to an oxygen now so carbon loses
those two electrons to oxygen.
Right, oxygen's more electronegative.
Oxygen takes, this top oxygen
takes those four electrons
and again, we split these two electrons.
So, this time carbon is
only surrounded by one.
So, define carbon's oxidation state
we know that carbon's supposed
to have four valence electrons
and from that we subtract the number
of valence electrons around carbon
once we've accounted
for electronegativity.
And that's only one electron now.
So, four minus one gives us
an oxidation state of plus three.
So, on the right this same carbon
now has an oxidation state of plus three.
So, what happened in this reaction?
Carbon went from an
oxidation state of plus one
to an oxidation state of plus three.
An increase in the oxidation
state is oxidation.
So, our starting compound
was oxidized here.
So, our starting compound was oxidized.
In order for this to be oxidized
we would need some sort
of oxidizing agent.
So, I'll write that down
here really quickly.
We would need an oxidizing agent
to accomplish this reaction.
And it's the oxidizing agent that itself
is being reduced because remember,
whenever something is being oxidized
something else has to be reduced.
Let's think about the
other definitions for,
the other definition I
should say for oxidation.
We know that oxidation
involves the loss of electrons.
So, let's look at that here.
On the left, right, carbon
had three electrons around it,
and when we added a bond to oxygen,
right, carbon lost these
two electrons over here.
It had those two electrons.
On the left it had those two electrons.
On the right it lost those two electrons
and now it's only surrounded by one.
And we see an increase
in the oxidation state.
So, it's like carbon lost electrons.
Also there's a shortcut that you can use.
For this reaction, let's think about
what that shortcut would be.
Let me use, I'll use red still.
On the left, this carbon with
an oxidation state of plus one
has two bonds to oxygen.
Let me go ahead and highlight them here.
So, here's one bond and
here's the other bond.
On the right, that same carbon now
has three bonds to oxygen.
So, here's one bond, here's two bonds,
and then this bond over here.
So, we've increased in the
number of bonds to oxygen
and that can tell us we have
an oxidation really quickly
without going through and doing
all these oxidation states.
Notice we lost a bond to hydrogen.
All right, so over here we
lost this bond to hydrogen
and we replaced it with a bond to oxygen.
So, an increase in the
number of bonds to oxygen
or a decrease in number
of bonds to hydrogen
can tell you that your
carbon is oxidized too.
Let's do another one.
So, our goal is to figure out
whether this starting compound has
been oxidized, reduced, or neither.
So, again, these three
carbons on the left, right,
are the same as these
three carbons on the right.
And there's no change in those carbons.
So, therefore we would expect no change
in the oxidation state.
The same with this carbon.
So, we're gonna focus in on this carbon.
So, on the left that
carbon has a double bond
to oxygen so we draw that in there
an then it's bonded to
a carbon on the left
and a carbon on the right.
And our product, that same carbon,
is now bonded to only one oxygen.
Let me go ahead and do that.
Only one bond I should say to oxygen
and it's still bonded
to a carbon on the left
and still bonded to a carbon on the right,
and it must have a bond to
hydrogen in here, right?
It's not drawn in but it's
assumed that you know that.
So, let's put in that bond to hydrogen.
And let's find our oxidation states.
So, we start on the left,
and we draw in our bonding electrons,
and next we think about
electronegativity differences.
So, we know that oxygen's more
electronegative than carbon
so oxygen takes those four electrons.
Over here, right, we assume
that the electronegativities
for these carbons are the same,
and so we split up those two electrons.
We give on electron to one carbon
and one electron to the other carbon.
And same over here.
So, the oxidation state for carbon
would be four valence electrons
minus this, in this case we have
two around carbon, so here's two.
Four minus two gives us an
oxidation state of plus two.
So, on the left this carbon has
an oxidation state of plus two.
What about on the right?
Let's put in our bonding electrons
and again, once we've
done that we think about
electronegativity and we can assign
an oxidation state to that carbon.
So, we know that oxygen's
more elecrtonegative
so oxygen takes those two electrons.
Right, again, there's, we assume
that these carbons have
the same electronegativity
so we split up those electrons.
We split up these electrons.
But now carbon is bonded to hydrogen.
So, carbon is a little
more electronegative
than hydrogen so we just give both
of those electrons to carbon.
And now let's find our oxidation state.
We know carbon is supposed to have
four valence electrons around it
and in our drawing here, once we've
accounted for electronegativity
carbon is surrounded by
one, two, three, and four.
So, four minus four is equal to zero.
And so this carbon, this carbon now
has an oxidation state of zero.
So, that carbon went
from an oxidation state
of plus two to an oxidation state of zero.
That's a decrease in the oxidation state.
So, carbon was reduced.
So, in this reaction our
starting compound was reduced.
All right, so this was, our
starting compound was reduced
which means we would need
some sort of reducing agent
to accomplish this reaction.
And it's the reducing agent
that would be oxidized
because if something is reduced
something else has to be oxidized.
We can also think about our
other definition for reduction.
Gain of electrons is reduction
and let's look at what happened here.
So, the electrons that were gained right,
were these two electrons right here
because on the left we had this carbon
with a double bond to this oxygen.
On the right, we have only
now one bond to oxygen.
Right, so we gained these two electrons
because we increased the
number of bonds to hydrogen.
So, our other shortcut is to look
at the number of bonds to oxygen.
Like we talked about in the last example.
On the left, carbon has
a double bond to oxygen.
So, two bonds to oxygen.
On the right we have
only one bond to oxygen.
So, we decreased in the
number of bonds to oxygen
so that's a reduction.
Again, a fast way of figuring it out.
Or we increased an number
of bonds to hydrogen.
Let's do one more of these problems.
So, our goal is to figure out
if our starting compound on the left
has been oxidized, reduced, or neither.
And this time these are the two carbons
that we are going to analyze.
Those are the two carbons
that have changed in this reaction.
So, on the left let's draw what we have.
We have a carbon with a
double bond to another carbon
and both of those carbons are bonded to,
directly bonded to two more carbons.
On the right, those carbons now
only have a single bond between them
and this carbon on the left
is bonded to a hydrogen.
This carbon on the right is
directly bonded to an oxygen
and let's put in those
other carbons, right?
We have another carbon, carbon bonds.
I mean, let's put in those
carbon, carbon bonds like that.
Let's assign our oxidation states.
So, we draw in our bonding electrons
and we think about
electronegativity differences
but we're going assume once again
that our carbons have the same
electronegativity on the left
and so when we're assigning electrons
let's just pick one of those carbons.
So, let's pick the carbon
on the left, right?
We divide up those two
electrons in that bond.
Give one electron to one carbon.
One electron to the other.
We do the same thing here.
And for the double bond
with four electrons
we divide up those four electrons.
We give two electrons to each carbon.
And so carbon is supposed to
have four valence electrons
and around it, this carbon
has one, two, three, and four.
So, four minus four is an
oxidation state of zero.
So, this carbon has an
Same thing for the carbon on the
right side of the double bond, right?
So, the same situation.
So, it also has an
oxidation state of zero.
What about for our product, right?
Let's examine those two carbons.
Let's put in our bonding electrons.
So, we draw in our bonding electrons here.
So, we put those in.
A lot more bonding electrons to draw.
And we think about electronegativity
differences, right?
Things have changed.
So, now, now let's focus in
on the carbon on the left.
So, the carbon on the left
is now bonded to a hydrogen
and carbon is a little
bit more electronegative.
So, we give both of
those electrons to carbon
and then we have carbon bonded to carbon,
carbon bonded to carbon,
and carbon bonded to carbon.
So, what's the oxidation state
of that carbon on the left now?
Carbon is supposed to have
four valence electrons
and how many do have around it?
Let's see, one, two, three, four, five.
So, four minus five gives us
an oxidation state of minus one.
So, this carbon on the left now has
What about the carbon on the right?
Well, we have a tie here, right?
So, we divide up those
electrons, a tie here,
but oxygen is more
electronegative than carbon.
So, oxygen gets both of those electrons.
So, the carbon on the right should have
an oxidation state of for minus three.
Here are the three electrons around carbon
once we've accounted
for electronegativity.
So, that's an oxidation state of plus one.
So, this carbon has an
oxidation state of plus one.
So, overall, what happened here?
Well, let me use red.
So, the carbon on the left went from
an oxidation state of zero
to an oxidation state of minus one.
That is a decrease in the oxidation state.
So, that carbon was reduced.
What about the carbon on the right side
of the double bond that
we started off with?
It started off with an
oxidation state of zero
and it went to an oxidation
state of plus one.
That's an increase in the oxidation state.
So, that carbon was oxidized.
What can we say about
starting compounds overall?
Well, the starting compound overall
there's no net change in
the oxidation states, right?
So, on the left for those two carbons
we get a total of zero.
On the right we had negative
one and positive one
for a total of zero.
There's no net change.
So, this would be neither.
The starting compound was, overall,
it wasn't oxidized or
reduced. It's neither.